#### Curriculum Vitae

## **Peter Berrill**

Born: 18<sup>th</sup> May, 1989 E-mail: peter.berrill@aya.yale.edu

Nationality: Irish peter.berrill@tu-berlin.de

## PERSONAL PROFILE

Peter is an industrial ecologist, working on issues related to urban sustainability and is an active researcher in the fields of environmental assessment and climate change mitigation, with foci in the building, energy, and transport sectors. He has a background in energy system and civil engineering, and much of his research deals with embodied, operation, and indirect (e.g. influence of urban built environments on transport emissions) environmental impacts of buildings and long-lived infrastructure. His current research project explores integrated approaches for reducing energy demand and emissions from transport and buildings in European cities. His research has employed key industrial ecology methods of life cycle assessment, material stock and flow analysis, and environmental footprinting, in addition to traditional and novel statistical techniques, building energy simulation, and energy system analysis.

## **EDUCATION**

2016 – 2021	Doctor of Philosophy in Industrial Ecology – Yale University (USA).
	Thesis: "Energy and emissions in the U.S. residential sector, historical perspectives
	and opportunities for climate change mitigation". Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
2013 - 2015	Master of Science in Industrial Ecology – Double degree awarded by University of
	Graz (Austria) & TU Delft/Leiden University (Netherlands).
	Thesis Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
2014 - 2015	Master of Science – Waseda University (Japan), study exchange
2015	Master of Science – Norwegian University of Science and Technology Industrial
	Ecology Programme (Norway), research exchange
2009 - 2013	Bachelor of Engineering in Energy Systems Engineering, with minor in Civil
	Engineering – National University of Ireland, Galway (Ireland). Result: 1.1
	Thesis Supervisor Jamie Goggins
2008 - 2009	Higher Certificate in Music Performance – Royal Conservatoire of Scotland (UK)

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2021-Present	Marie-Curie Individual Fellowship experienced researcher, TU Berlin;	
	Guest Researcher, MCC Berlin (Germany)	
2020	Doctoral intern researcher, Residential Buildings Research Group, National	
	Renewable Energy Laboratory (USA)	
2016-2021	Researcher and Doctoral Candidate, Yale University, Centre for Industrial	
	Ecology (USA)	
2016	Business English Instructor, IBEC (Japan)	
2015	Researcher, Industrial Ecology Programme, Norwegian University of Science and	
	Technology (Norway)	
2012	Intern civil, environmental engineer, Alan Kerins Project (Ireland, Zambia)	
2009 – 2016	Musician and Music Tutor, EMK Productions and Freelance (Ireland)	

## **ACADEMIC SERVICE & SOCIETY MEMBERSHIP**

Board Member: International Society for Industrial Ecology, Life Cycle Sustainability Assessment Section (2023-)

Member of Scientific Committee: International Conference on Industrial Ecology, Leiden (2023)

Society Member: International Society for Industrial Ecology (2016-)

Contributing Author: IPCC Assessment Report 6 Working Group 3, Buildings Chapter (2022)

Contributing Author: 'Ten insights from industrial ecology for the circular economy' (ISIE white paper, 2023)

Peter Berrill – C.V. July 2023

Student Representative on Faculty Search Committee: Yale School of the Environment, Professor in Industrial Ecology and Sustainable Systems (2020)

Leader of advisory group on reducing air travel GHG emissions from international conferences - International Society for Industrial Ecology

Academic Referee: Performed peer-reviews of articles submitted to *Journal of Industrial Ecology, Environmental Science & Technology, Environmental Research Letters, Joule, Scientific Data, Resources*,

Conservation & Recycling, Applied Energy, Nature Communications

#### **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

April 2021 Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Individual Fellowship (2yr) for project "Sustainable Urban Form For Integrated Climate Change Solutions" (SUFFICCS), €175,000 December 2018 Yale Institute for Biospheric Studies, Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grants, \$5,000 April 2017 Charles Kao Fund Research Grant, for project "Low-carbon Energy Development in 21st Century Japan", \$5,000 March 2014 Sole student to win competitive award for one-semester study exchange to Waseda University (Japan) as part of Erasmus Mundus MSc in Industrial Ecology Finalist in national competition for best final year project (bachelor thesis project) held by the September 2013 Republic of Ireland Regional Group of the Institution of Structural Engineers Erasmus Mundus Masters in Industrial Ecology (MIND) Category B scholarship award March 2013 (covering tuition, plus stipend totalling €16,000 over two years) National University of Ireland, Galway 'University Scholar', awarded to undergraduate September 2012 students achieving overall excellence, €500

### RESEARCH MENTORING EXPERIENCE

2023	Research mentor to early-stage doctoral student on project scoping and
	literature review related to high-resolution building materials stocks
2023	Research mentor to visiting master student for project on GIS and energy
	data in French buildings
2022	Research mentor to master student for MSc dissertation "Enhancing the
	sustainability of the residential sector with sufficiency measures"
2020	Research mentor to high-school student with Lumiere Education
2020	Research mentor to two masters students for summer internship research
	projects: "US economy-wide non-hazardous waste generation: an extension
	the us Input-Output tables", and "Comparison of physical vs economic
	allocation for airline GHG emissions"
2017	Research mentor to visiting masters student for thesis research project:
	"Assessment of the Embodied and Operational Trade-offs of a U.S. Multi-
	Family Building With Changing Energy Codes and Different Climate
	Zones"

## **OTHER SKILLS**

First Language: English

Other Languages (European CEFR level): Japanese (Independent – B1), German (Basic user – A2)

<u>Computer Programming Languages</u>:

Programming languages: R (advanced), Matlab (advanced), Python, including libraries for geospatial analysis (advanced), Google Earth Engine (basic), Bash/Shell (basic), Javascript (basic), ArcGIS / QGIS (basic)

#### ACADEMIC AND PROFESSIONAL PROFILES

ORCID: 0000-0003-1614-3885 github: https://github.com/peterberr

Google Scholar: <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PUMnjmMAAAAJ&hl=en">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PUMnjmMAAAAJ&hl=en</a>

LinkedIn: https://de.linkedin.com/in/peter-berrill-b56b7250

Website: <a href="https://peterberr.github.io/">https://peterberr.github.io/</a>

#### **SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS**

- Summary (Google Scholar): h-index (13), total citations (631 on July 7 2023)
- Peer-reviewed publications in scientific journals, as first author:
- **Berrill, P.**, E.J.H Wilson, J.L. Reyna, A.D. Fontanini and E.G. Hertwich. 2022. Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States, 2020-2060. *Nature Climate Change* 12(8): 712-718
- **Berrill, P.** & Hertwich, E. 2021. Material flows and GHG emissions from housing stock evolution in US counties, 2020-2060. *Buildings & Cities* 2(1): 599-617
- **Berrill, P.**, Gillingham, K. T., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Drivers of change in U.S. residential energy consumption and greenhouse gas emission, 1990-2015. *Environmental Research Letters* 16: 034045
- **Berrill, P.**, K.T. Gillingham and E.G. Hertwich. 2021. Influence of housing policy and housing typology on residential energy demand in the United States. *Environmental Science & Technology* 55(4): 2224-2233 http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c05696
- **Berrill, P.**, T.R. Miller, Y. Kondo, and E.G. Hertwich. 2020. Capital in the American carbon, energy, and material footprint. *Journal of Industrial Ecology* 24(3): 589–600.
- **Berrill, P.** and E.G. Hertwich. 2018. Ground truthing the environmental benefits of a polygeneration system: when to combine heat and power? *Energy & Buildings* 173: 221–238. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enbuild.2018.05.020.
- **Berrill, P.**, A. Arvesen, Y. Scholz, H.C. Gils, and E.G. Hertwich. 2016. Environmental impacts of high penetration renewable energy scenarios for Europe. *Environmental Research Letters* 10(12): 123002. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/11/1/014012

## Publications in preparation, as first author:

**Berrill, P.**, A. Javaid, N. Milojevic-Dupont, F. Nachtigall, F. Wagner, and F. Creutzig. 2023. Urban form influences travel distances, car ownership, and mode choice: evidence from 19 European cities. *Under Review* https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-2924076/v1

## Peer-reviewed publications in scientific journals, as co-author:

- Van Ewijk, S., Chaudhary, S., **Berrill, P**. 2023. Estimating passenger emissions from airfares supports equitable climate action. *Environmental Research Letters*
- Jiang, M., Suo, C., Wu, L., **Berrill, P**. 2022. Consumption structure optimization for reducing energy footprint. *Economic Systems Research*
- Wang, T., **Berrill, P.**, Zimmerman, J. B., Rao, N.D., Min, J., & Hertwich, E. G. 2022. Improved Copper Circularity as a Result of Increased Material Efficiency in the US Housing Stock. *Environmental Science and Technology*, 56(7), 4565-4577
- Pauliuk, S., Heeren, N., **Berrill, P.,** Fishman, T., Nistad, A., Tu, Q., Wolfram, P., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Global scenarios of resource and emission savings from material efficiency in residential buildings and cars. *Nature Communications*, 12(1), 5097
- Fishman, T., Heeren, N., Pauliuk, S., **Berrill, P.**, Tu, Q., Wolfram, P., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. A comprehensive set of global scenarios of housing, mobility, and material efficiency for material cycles and energy systems modeling. *Journal of Industrial Ecology*, 25(2), 305–320

- Wang, T., **Berrill, P.**, Zimmerman, J. B., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Copper Recycling Flow Model for the United States Economy: Impact of Scrap Quality on Potential Energy Benefit. *Environmental Science and Technology*, 55(8), 5485–5495
- Pauliuk, S., T. Fishman, N. Heeren, **P. Berrill**, Q. Tu, P. Wolfram, and E.G. Hertwich. 2020. Linking service provision to material cycles: A new framework for studying the resource efficiency–climate change (RECC) nexus. *Journal of Industrial Ecology*: 25(2), 260-273
- Miller, T.R., **P. Berrill**, P. Wolfram, R. Wang, Y. Kim, X. Zheng, and E.G. Hertwich. 2019. Method for endogenizing capital in the United States Environmentally-Extended Input-Output model. *Journal of Industrial Ecology* 23(6): 1410–1424.
- Wang, C., X. Zheng, W. Cai, X. Gao, and **P. Berrill**. 2017. Unexpected water impacts of energy-saving measures in the iron and steel sector: Tradeoffs or synergies? *Applied Energy*. 205: 1119-1127
- Reports, Book chapters, pre-prints, papers under review, and theses, as first and co-author:
- van Ewijk, S., Ashton, W. S., **Berrill, P.,** Cao, Z., Chertow, M., Chopra, S. S., Fishman, T., Fitzpatrick, C., Heidrich, O., Leipold, S., Ritter, F., Sprecher, B., Yao, Y., & Myers, R. J. (2023). *10 insights from industrial ecology for the circular economy*. https://is4ie.org/whitepaper
- Cabeza et al (2022) Chapter 9 Buildings, in IPCC AR6 Climate Change 2022 Mitigation of Climate Change
- Hertwich, E., Lifset, R., Pauliuk, S., Heeren, N., Ali, S., Tu, Q., Ardente, F., **Berrill, P.**, Fishman, T., Kanaoka, K., Kulczycka, J., Makov, T., Masanet, E., & Wolfram, P. (2020). *Resource Efficiency and Climate Change: Material Efficiency Strategies for a Low-Carbon Future*.
- Chertow, M.R., K.S. Kanaoka, T.R. Miller, **P. Berrill**, P. Wolfram, N. Heeren, and T. Fishman. 2020. The Systems Science of Industrial Ecology: Tools and Strategies Toward Meeting the Sustainable Development Goals. In *Science, Technology, and Innovation for Sustainable Development Goals*, ed. by Adenle A. Ademola, Marian R. Chertow, Ellen H. M. Moors, and David J. Pannell. Oxford University Press.
- **Berrill, P.** 2021. A Comparison of Strategies for Mitigation of Lifecycle Greenhouse Gases from Residential Buildings in the United States (Doctoral Thesis) Yale University. Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
- **Berrill, P.** 2015. Life cycle assessment of power systems with large shares of variable renewable energy (Masters Thesis) University of Graz. Supervisors Edgar G. Hertwich, Anders Arvesen
- **Berrill, P.**, Moran, P. 2013 Environmental Life Cycle Assessment of a University Building in Ireland (Bachelors Thesis) National University of Ireland, Galway. Supervisor Jamie Goggins

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**:

Academic Teaching fellow posts:

2022Urban Economics for Sustainability (Seminar), with Prof. Felix Creutzig2020Industrial Ecology, with Prof. Marian Chertow and Dr. Stijn van Ewijk2019Energy Systems Analysis, with Prof. Narasimha Rao2019, 2017Green Building: Issues and Perspectives, with Mr. Peter Yost2018Energy Systems Analysis, with Prof. Edgar Hertwich2017Carbon Footprints: Modelling and Analysis, with Prof. Edgar Hertwich

Non-Academic Teaching experience:

2023 Tutor with 'Prometeruse' project which connects scientists with secondary

school students who develop a mini-research into a question related to

climate change

2009-2016 Trumpet Tutor to individual beginner trumpet students

Teaching training and qualifications:

2020 'Planning a Seminar or Lecture for an English-Speaking

> Audience', training at TU Berlin. Aimed at inclusive teaching of students with various cultural backgrounds whose first language is

not necessarily English

Teaching English as a Foreign Language certificate from i-to-i, 2016

accredited by Open and Distance Learning Quality Council

Selected guest classroom lectures:

2020 & 2021 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: Impacts Embodied in Trade 2019

Guest lecture in Green Building: Issues and Perspectives course:

"Trends and drivers of US residential energy consumption, 1990-

2015"

2018 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: "Input-Output Life Cycle

Assessment"

2017 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: "Life Cycle Assessment -

Introduction"

## ORAL PRESENTATIONS AT SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES

Invited Presentation

30/06/2020: "Estimation of demolition and new construction of housing in US counties until 2060 -Implications for building material reuse potential" - The 15th International Conference on Waste Management and Technology Zero-waste City High Level Forum (Online)

Presentations

05/07/2023: "Influence of Urban Form on Car Ownership, Mode Choice, and Travel Distance in European Cities" - International Society for Industrial Ecology 2023, Leiden (Netherlands)

20/09/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" - International Society for Industrial Ecology – Socioeconomic Metabolism Conference, Wien (Austria)

03/06/2022: "Building and Shelter" Session chair and introductory presentation – ECCC Symposium, Berlin (Germany)

25/05/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" – International Energy Workshop, Freiburg (Germany)

03/06/2020: "Housing policy, housing typology, and residential energy in the United States" - Actionable Science for Urban Sustainability (Online)

08/07/2019: "Dynamic stock, energy and lifecycle analysis of residential buildings in the US" - 10th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Beijing (China)

11/04/2019: "Drivers of residential energy consumption in the US and options for GHG reductions" – Yale FES Research Day, New Haven (USA)

20/04/2018: "Making less bad things happen when we build houses and make our homes feel warm" (Up-Goer-Five presentation) – Yale FES Research Day, New Haven (USA)

28/06/2017: "Environmental performance of university campus buildings: An energy system evaluation" 9th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Chicago (USA)

28/09/2016: "Life Cycle Analysis of Electricity Systems: High Penetration Renewable Scenarios and the Roles of Energy Storage and Grid Transmission" - American Center for Life Cycle Assessment, LCA XVI, Charlestown (USA)

Peter Berrill – C.V. July 2023

03/06/2016: "Environmental impacts of high penetration renewable energy scenarios for Europe" – International Energy Workshop, Cork (Ireland)

### **INVITED SEMINAR PRESENTATIONS**

- 12/05/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" MCC (Germany)
- 01/11/2019: "Drivers of change in residential energy consumption in the US, 1990-2015,

  The roles of housing age cohorts, fuel switching, and household size" Yale University (USA)
- 08/06/2018: "Reducing carbon, energy, and material footprints from the residential sector in the united states: the importance of capital stocks and energy supply systems" Waseda University, Tokyo (Japan)
- 03/08/2017: "Accounting for consumption of capital in the US Input-Output tables: approaches and impacts" Waseda University, Tokyo (Japan)

#### POSTER PRESENTATIONS AT SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES/SCIENCE OUTREACH EVENTS

- 10/09/2022: "Urban form's influence on GHG intensity of urban mobility in European cities" Berlin Klima Tag 2022 (Germany)
- 21/06/2021: "Pathways for sustainable material use and GHG emission reductions from housing stock evolution in US counties to 2060" Industrial Ecology Day 2021 (Online)
- 23/05/2018: "Reducing carbon, energy, and material footprints from the residential sector in the US: The importance of capital stocks and energy supply systems" Industrial Ecology Gordon Research Conference, Les Diablerets (Switzerland)
- 27/06/2017: "Environmental performance of university campus buildings: An energy system evaluation" 9th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Chicago (USA)